Guide to the New Orleans and the Levees
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
New Orleans and the Levees
2015
GEN MSS 1470
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.17
1 box
Twenty photographs of sites and portraits of people on and near levees surrounding New Orleans, Louisiana, created by Karen Halverson in spring 2015. Images include views of buildings and ships as well as people in Orleans Parish and Jefferson Parish.
Halverson, Karen, 1941-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Karen Halverson on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2016.
Arrangement
Arranged by the creator.
Karen Halverson (born 1941)
Karen Halverson is a documentary landscape photographer. Born in Syracuse, New York, Halverson received a Bachelor of Arts from Stanford University and Masters of Arts from Brandeis University and Columbia University. In 1975, she made her first photographic project, which documented the Garment District in New York City. Much of her work documents the tension between the natural and cultural landscapes of the American West. She is the author of Downstream: Encounters with the Colorado River (University of California Press, 2008), which retraces the route of John Wesley Powell's expeditions and explores what contemporary Americans have made of the waterway.
Description of Papers
Views of sites and portraits of people on and near levees surrounding New Orleans, Louisiana, created by Karen Halverson in spring 2015 and printed as color inkjet prints on Canson Platine Fibre Rag Paper, 20 x 24 inches (51 x 61 centimeters). Images include views of buildings and ships as well as people in Orleans Parish except where noted in the guide. The prints are untitled with parenthetical numbers provided by Halverson to differentiate images. The collection comprises an edition numbered three of twelve.
In an artist's statement that accompanied the collection upon acquisition in 2016, Halverson describes the work:
For many years, much of my work as a photographer has focused on the human relationship to the landscape. Recently, I headed to New Orleans, a city with a unique and precarious relationship to its natural environment. New Orleans sits in a bowl, half of it below sea level, edged by the Mississippi River to the South, wetlands to the West, and large lakes North and East. It is a city that requires a complex system of levees and underground pumps to stay dry. Within a few days of arriving in New Orleans; I decided to photograph the levees themselves, the views they afford, and the people who make use of them.
In 1718, the French established the settlement of New Orleans along a natural levee made up of silt deposited by the Mississippi River. Ever since colonial times, man-made levees, either earthen berms or concrete walls, have been built against the surrounding waters. But the man-made levees also prevent natural silt deposition. As a result, New Orleans is sinking while, at the same time, sea levels are rising due to climate change.
There have been dozens of hurricanes over the centuries, but Hurricane Katrina, in 2005, was epic. Eighty percent of the city was flooded. It is now well established that the design and construction of the levees were seriously flawed. Since Katrina, they have been rebuilt based on computer-generated models of potential storms.
Although the levees are meant for flood control, from early on they also served another purpose. Gentlemen and "free colored courtesans" (Thomas Ashe, Travels in America, 1811) gathered on them in search of fresh air. Today the levees are popular strolling places for the great mix of people who live in or visit New Orleans. From most points in the city, the levees block the view of the Mississippi River. So, a walk along the levee offers not only fresh air and a chance to mingle, but also a look at the business of the river, the huge shipping facilities and oil refineries that line the river's edge and that reflect a significant part of the New Orleans economy. This series of photographs, New Orleans and the Levees, is the result of my stroll along the levees during the spring of 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Levees -- Louisiana -- Jefferson Parish -- Pictorial works; Levees -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- Pictorial works; Levees -- Louisiana -- Orleans Parish -- Pictorial works; Jefferson Parish (La.) -- Pictorial works; Jefferson Parish (La.) -- Portraits; Louisiana -- Pictorial works; New Orleans (La.) -- Pictorial works; New Orleans (La.) -- Portraits; Orleans Parish (La.) -- Pictorial works; Orleans Parish (La.) -- Portraits; Inkjet prints; Photographs; Karen Halverson; Halverson, Karen, 1941-
- New Orleans and the Levees, 2015
  Scope and Contents
  Views of sites and portraits of people on and near levees surrounding New Orleans, Louisiana, created by Karen Halverson in spring 2015 and printed as color inkjet prints on Canson Platine Fibre Rag Paper, 20 x 24 inches (51 x 61 centimeters). Images include views of buildings and ships as well as people in Orleans Parish except where noted in the guide. The prints are untitled with parenthetical numbers provided by Halverson to differentiate images. The collection comprises an edition numbered three of twelve.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by the creator.
  - Untitled ( 6604 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Untitled ( 5319 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled ( 5596 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Untitled ( 5860 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Untitled ( 5512 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Untitled ( 6338 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photograph of a site in Jefferson Parish
  - Untitled ( 5874 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Untitled ( 5826 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Untitled ( 6029 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Untitled ( 5885 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Untitled ( 6040 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Untitled ( 6460 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Untitled ( 5181 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Untitled ( 6547 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Untitled ( 5867 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Untitled ( 5853 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Untitled ( 5570 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Untitled ( 6286 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Untitled ( 6517 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Untitled ( 6688 ), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 20)